<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>uncertain augur</title>
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io" />
    <id>https://uncertain-augur.github.io/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name></name>
        <email></email>
    </author>
    <updated>2019-09-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Intro</title>
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io/posts/intro/index.html" />
    <id>https://uncertain-augur.github.io/posts/intro/index.html</id>
    <published>2019-09-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-09-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../images/tokyo_comp.jpg" /> <span class="marginnote"> <a href="https://flic.kr/p/BA9Cye">Tokyo. B. Lucava</a> </span></p>
<p>The world is a confusing place. This is a notebook of my attempts to understand it.</p>
<p>Exactly what form that will take remains to be seen. This blog is one part of an ongoing project to better understand world. I was originally trained as an engineer, but I’ve always had a fascination with decision making and strategy; I want to understand the mental tools people develop to try to survive and thrive in an uncertain and sometimes adversarial world. Toward the end of my university career, these interests found some overlap, and I focused on robotics, learning how to answer questions of uncertainty and decision making precisely in artificial systems.</p>
<p>As I kept reading and learning, my interests keep drawing me back to certain themes. I’d see connections that I didn’t understand, but that seemed meaningful. Commonalities between image-recognition neural networks and sections of the human brain. Mathematical structures of game theory that pop up in robotic agents, online auction markets, and evolutionary biology. Concepts from nonlinearity and chaos theory mapped onto Clausewitz. Ideas of emergent complexity that try to explain the structures of anthills, markets, and civilizations. Over and over, I feel like I keep seeing common roots in complexity theory - chaos and emergence, nonlinearity and evolution.</p>
<p>These connections have all been drawn by far smarter people than myself. I simply keep coming across them, and they bother me, like an object moving in the corner of my vision that I can never bring into my line of sight. It’s possible, one day, that someone will produce some unified theory of emergent complexity that will make these connections clear. For now, however, we will have to be content with drawing on range of domains, building up an array of overlapping lenses with which to look at the world. As we go, we can make note of these connections where we come across them, and try to sketch little bits of the grand structure that come into view.</p>
<p>For myself, I’m trying to go about that in a more structured way, and this blog is part of that. Early on, I expect a lot of notes, while I try to digest what others already know. I’m still at the stage where I should speak less and listen more. As time goes on and my thoughts develop a little more, I hope to add a little more of my own synthesis.</p>
<p>Finally, although complexity and the adjacent domains it leaks into are all fascinating in their own right, this isn’t a purely academic project. I’m an engineer by training, and the idea of building things is close to my heart. I’m interested in decision making not just for its own sake, but to improve my own choices. Nonlinear systems, systems that evolve in response to outside stimuli, systems deeply intertwined with human and economic dynamics- in short, the sort of systems that complexity science is interested in - are exactly the ones where our traditional engineering approaches break down. I’m interested in the idea that by studying these systems, we can not only appreciate the beauty of the world, but build up a Munger-style library of mental models and heuristics to help us navigate them better. Cultivating complex sociotechnical systems is a weird blend of systems engineering, gardening, and conflict, trying to solve a problem that in some ways is trying to solve you back.</p>
<p>I don’t know if it’s possible to get better at it, but I’m interested to try. I hope that you find something here of use.</p>
<h3 id="image-credits">Image Credits</h3>
<ul>
<li>Lucava, B. Tokyo. Online image. <a href="https://flic.kr/p/BA9Cye" class="uri">https://flic.kr/p/BA9Cye</a></li>
</ul>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
