<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>uncertain augur</title>
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io" />
    <id>https://uncertain-augur.github.io/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name></name>
        <email></email>
    </author>
    <updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>Baseball, Fighter Pilots, and Trauma Medicine: Good Decisions with Heuristics</title>
    <link href="https://uncertain-augur.github.io/posts/fftrees/index.html" />
    <id>https://uncertain-augur.github.io/posts/fftrees/index.html</id>
    <published>2020-06-06T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../../images/spitfire.jpg" /></p>
<p>There’s a fascinating wing of decision science called ecological rationality. This work studies the problem of how it is that people are able to make decisions in the real world, under pressure, and in the face of what from an academic standpoint look like overwhelming information processing requirements. We are able to do this by using heuristics, decision rules that aggressively filter available information to focus on a few key signals.</p>
<p>The 101 example of this is the gaze heuristic, which emerges when someone (or something) is trying to solve the problem of intercepting a moving object, such as a catcher trying to catch an incoming flying ball. A computer program designed to solve this problem and plan the runner’s path might model the physics of the system, compute a trajectory for the ball, solve for the optimal impact point, and then move to that point. If it were an online system, it might update its estimates of the parameters of the ball in-flight, checking the ball’s movement against its internal model, and refining its estimate at each step.</p>
<p>It’s clear that no human being can replicate this method. What is interesting is that we don’t appear to even approximate it. Trying to divine the internal reasoning processes of human beings is a challenging and finicky science, but we find no evidence in either neurobiology or conversations with expert athletes for a “physics model” type of process. Instead, the solution is simple: fix your eye on the ball, and move so that the angle of your eye doesn’t change. If you do this, your path will coincide with that of the ball<span><label for="sn-1" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-1" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">Of course, nothing in life is this simple. Prior to the throw, the catcher’s brain would be processing an incredible amount of sensory input and associative memory, ranging from the intentions of the thrower to the direction of the wind. While running, the catcher would (hopefully) avoid obstacles, and in the terminal phase a complex set of conscious and trained/unconscious muscle patterns would come in to play. However, the basic point- that the core planning task was accomplished by focusing on a very small subset of the potential information available- holds true.<br />
<br />
</span></span>. This appears over and over again, wherever variations on this problem are found: anywhere from Ultimate Frisbee to the hunting behaviours of predatory animals and bomber-interception strategies employed by RAF pilots during WWII. <img src="../../images/cheetah-hunting.jpg" /> <span class="marginnote"> Figure: A decision professional employing the gaze heuristic at work. </span></p>
<p>The gaze heuristic is an example of what the leading researcher in this field, Gerd Gigerenzer refers to as a one-clever-cue heuristic<span><label for="sn-2" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-2" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">Heuristic Decision Making. Gigerenzer and Gaissmaier, 2011. Annu. Rev. Psychol. 2011.62:451-82.<br />
<br />
</span></span>, focusing on a single piece of crucial information to the exclusion of everything else that might be relevant. This is one of many types of heuristics in the literature, showing how we can handle decision, classification, and resource-allocation problems with restricted amounts of information. Much of this work deals with understanding how human cognitive processes work, and reflects the ongoing academic battle between the ecological rationality school and students of Kahneman and Tversky’s work (somewhat confusingly referred to as the heuristics and biases school) that views heuristics as flaws or deviations from rational decision-making.</p>
<p>The scientific debate is interesting, but for the practically minded, not obviously useful. For that matter, neither is the gaze heuristic, unless your day-to-day work involves gazelle predation or engagements with the Luftwaffe. When we try to extract more general principles, the unifying theme of Gigernezer’s work is that these heuristics are “ecologically rational”- somewhat tautologically, rational heuristics are ones that tend to work in the environment in which they are employed. As advice goes, “only focus on the information that matters” is only marginally more useful than “try not to lose”. However, I believe that there is, in fact, significant pragmatic value here, and that understanding how we use heuristics naturally can guide us in how we think, decide, and learn.</p>
<p>To think about how this might actually help with our own decision flow, let’s shift domains, and take two examples from a different field that nevertheless requires quick decision-making: emergency medicine.</p>
<p>The first example is a well-studied research case from the ecological rationality literature, where emergency room physicians used a heuristic tool to sort patients into high and low-risk categories for heart attacks. The tool used was slightly more complex than the gaze heuristic: doctors were given three signs to check, in a specific order, with thresholds given for each value to classify as good or bad.. For each cue, one result meant an immediate decision (the rest of the checks were ignored), while patients falling into the other category had the next vital checked, and the process repeated. No information was considered a second time; no looping back. You might recognize this process as a decision tree, albeit a heavily pruned one. This specific structure is referred to as a fast-and-frugal tree, or FFT<span><label for="sn-3" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-3" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">The unfortunate naming overlap with the fast Fourier transform is usually unimportant in psychology, and aggravating in machine learning.<br />
<br />
</span></span>. In an FFT, each piece of information is only considered once, and each decision node has at least one branch that leads to an immediate decision.<br />
<img src="../../images/cardio-fft.png" /> <span class="marginnote"> The fast-and-frugal tree for cardiac risk assessment used in emergency rooms by Green and Mehr, 1997. </span></p>
<p>There are a couple of interesting things to note about this tool. First, it does well: under test conditions, the heuristic was competitive with a logistic-regression model that considered many more variable simultaneously<span><label for="sn-4" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-4" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">In fact, it outperformed the model under many circumstances. This appears to be due to a tendency to get less confused by anomalies or outliers in either the training or test data, or more technically, robustness to overfitting. The ability of simple rules to sometimes outperform more complicated models, even when thinking/computation time is not a limiting factor, is an interesting topic for another time- suffice to say that it can both help us understand why, exactly, heuristics work so well in nature, and possibly provide some clues for dealing with complex real-world systems, where any practical amount of computation may still be insufficient.<br />
<br />
</span></span>. What’s more, doctors were much more willing to use it. Not only was it more convenient than a computer program, but it provided an comprehensible logic that the regression model’s inscrutable, black-box judgements lacked.</p>
<p>Second: unlike the gaze heuristic, which emerges naturally in humans and animals, this heuristic was deliberately designed. The cues and threshold values for the branches of the tree were chosen by experts, who had the luxury of time and contemplation not available to the doctor standing at a bedside in the ER. The tree provides a way of compressing that expertise, data, and deliberation down into a format that’s usable and accessible by someone else in the field. Teaching someone to think like a regression model is impossible, getting them to run to a computer to use one in a high-pressure environment is often impractical, but something as simple as the tree above can be committed to memory or a pocket notepad, and kept no more than a second away.</p>
<p><img src="../../images/uk-mountain-first-aid.jpg" /> <span class="marginnote"> UK Mountain Rescue team providing remote first aid. Wilderness emergency medicine provides a rich library of situations where people (who often are not full-time medical professionals) have to make challenging, highly consequential decisions under time pressure, with limited diagnostic tools, few options, and no external decision support. </span></p>
<p>The second example is also from emergency medicine, this time first aid, and will be familiar to many more of you- the ABCDE initial assessment<span><label for="sn-5" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-5" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">I’m using the one that I was originally taught here: Airway, breathing, circulation, disability (spinal injury), and environmental exposure. There are a number of variations, as we will discuss.<br />
<br />
</span></span> procedure for CPR and first aid. This is typically taught as a priority list of procedures: check the airway. If obstructed, immediately stop and clear. Otherwise, move on to check for breathing, and so forth. Although this isn’t typically thought of as a heuristic or FFT, I would argue that it meets our definition. First, we aggressively filter information. In the event that a patient is not noticeably breathing, we move immediately to CPR without checking for a pulse, because most of the time, the cost of inaction is much more significant than the rare cases where the patient is not breathing but has a heartbeat. Second, we fit the fast-and-frugal tree structure: we check each cue, sequentially, and if it is unacceptable, we take immediate corrective action. One cue, one exit node.</p>
<p>The interesting point here is not that viewing ABCDE or other first-aid procedures as heuristics immediately makes us better medics, but for the implications for planning and training. The ABCDE assessment is universal for a reason: it works, and it helps people in extremely stressful circumstances act appropriately. I would argue that this, at least in part, is because it provides a frugal decision tree structure that fits smoothly into how we naturally think. We are not, as a rule, good at weighing large numbers of variables simultaneously. We are very good at focusing on specific cues and deciding if we consider them to be good or bad. Having an external structure lets us do this in a way that’s reliable, easily communicated<span><label for="sn-6" class="margin-toggle sidenote-number"></label><input type="checkbox" id="sn-6" class="margin-toggle"/><span class="sidenote">I speculate, but I imagine that if you took a class of novice first-aiders, and drilled them on the physiology behind the ABC assessment without actually teaching it, they would simply re-invent it after a couple rounds of scenario training. Each medic would understand the importance of airway, checking for major bleeding, and so forth, and develop a list of cues and classifications in order to do this. The difference, of course, is that this would take longer to learn, and consistency/communication between teammates would be much harder.<br />
<br />
</span></span>, and transparent. With an explicit heuristic, it’s possible for teams to both communicate and learn scientifically (such as the recent move, coming from the TCCC community, to move hemorrhage management to before airway) in a way would be much harder if each caregiver were following an internal, less conscious list of rules.</p>
<p>So, we’ve now seen two examples of deliberately designed FFT heuristics: one from the research literature, one widespread tool from first aid that also happens to fit our definition. So, what are the takeaways here?</p>
<p>The first is the core message of the ecological rationality school: heuristics can work. Relatively simple rules, focusing on a small amount of the available information, let us make correct decisions that matter in real world situations, not just when studying toy problems.</p>
<p>The second is that heuristic tools prove easy to adopt and teach. Again, I would argue that this is because they reflect and augment how we already think. In martial arts or other athletics, we use techniques that reflect our natural biomechanics and maximize their potential, rather than trying to force our bodies into movements for which they’re ill-suited. In the same way, heuristics give us a way of structuring decisions that fits our mental biomechanics. The fact that ABC is a convenient acronym is helpful, but that’s not why it’s a useful tool (as many, many excruciating failed acronyms can attest). It’s useful because it takes what we’d do anyway, checking cues and classifying them as good/bad, and infuses it with our collective, conscious knowledge of medicine and biology.</p>
<p>Finally, I think this is something you can use when trying to work on your own thought and decision processes. Recognize that when your rational, System 2 resources are insufficient (either because you’re under time/resource pressure, or because the world is often simply too complex to model and comprehend) you’re going to default to using heuristics. If you do this unconsciously, you run the risk that they don’t reflect your best conscious understanding of the world (a source of “wait, why did I do that?” moments) or worse, are actively irrational, originating from unrepresentative one-off experiences or past traumatic incidents.</p>
<p>Next time you reflect on a decision you had to make under uncertain circumstances, try sketching a tree like the one above, and see how well it describes your thinking. What did you worry about? What cues were you using? Where were the cutoffs, and what different information would have given you pause or changed your mind?</p>
<p>Likewise, when you’re planning, reflecting on a problem, or preparing a training scenario (for yourself, or others) play around with looking at things in terms of cues and cutoffs, rules of thumb and frugal trees. If you ended up having to make a decision, lacking time, lacking information, how would you aim to get things right most of the time? The goal here, to use Kahneman’s terminology, is to bring your System 1 and System 2 into alignment: your conscious, reflective System 2 mind should be aware of what your System 1 mind will do in the moment, and your System 1 should- as much as possible- be equipped with the best of what your conscious mind has worked so hard to learn and understand.</p>]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
